Perry Egbert Papers
Perry Egbert Papers
1911-1987
1925-1945
Egbert, Perry T.
6 linear ft.
American engineer, worked for American Locomotive Company (ALCo). Correspondence, technical reports and drawings, cost information, etc., most of which relates to ALCo and its production of diesel engines.
4018018
Biographical History
Perry T. Egbert was an American engineer specializing in internal combustion engines, particularly diesel engines. Most of his career was spent at the American Locomotive Company (ALCo), America's pre-eminent manufacturer of steam and diesel locomotives for more than forty years.
Egbert received a degree in mechanical engineering from Cornell University in 1915 and, after a stint in the military during World War I, taught experimental engineering at his alma mater in 1919 and 1920. In 1921 he became ALCo's technical representative in East Asia, including efforts to provide diesel engines for the Peking Suiyuan Railway. Following the acquisition of the firm of McIntosh and Seymour in 1929 he was placed in charge of ALCo's diesel engine development program. He became manager of railroad diesel sales in 1934 and vice president in charge of diesel locomotive sales in 1944. After World War II, he led ALCo's shift from steam to diesel locomotive production. He became president of the company in 1952.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from "Alco versus EMD," UtahRails.Net, http://utahrails.net/articles/alco-v-emd.php.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Perry Egbert Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, subject files, technical data and writings, and spans more than thirty years of his career with the American Locomotive Company (ALCo). Almost all of the collection relates directly to ALCo's production and sales of diesel engines, but there is also material relating to ALCo's competitor Electro-Motive Corporation (EMC), which later became the Electro-Motive Division of General Electric (EMD), and subsidiary companies Montreal Locomotive Works and McIntosh and Seymour. Rail lines mentioned in the collection include Chicago and Western, Delaware Lackawanna & Western (DL&W), Los Angeles & Salt Lake (LA&SL), Lehigh Valley, Wabash, Burmeister & Wayne, Peking Suiyuan (China), and others.
Correspondence covers Egbert's early years as East Asian representative up through his time as vice president in charge of diesel locomotive sales. The period from 1920 to 1925 includes extensive material related to ALCo's involvement with the Peking Suiyuan Railway -- telegrams (some of them in code), reports on meetings, correspondence with various Chinese banking and government officials, etc. -- and to the rail industry in China in general. Other topics include reports from the field, investigations of various engine part failures, cost comparisons, labor negotiations, discussion of new designs, and more.
Memorabilia includes two cartoons (one featuring Egbert by name), various railroad-related social club ephemera, business cards, a patent agreement between Egbert and ALCo, and a souvenir / public relations booklet from ALCo competitor Electro-Motive Corporation (EMC) about the company. Also included here is a folder of photographs, the subjects of which include ALCo meetings, railyards, equipment, a clay model of engine and an artist's rendering of the interior of a locomotive cab.
Printed material consists of material both by ALCo and other companies or organizations. ALCo material includes more than twenty years of annual reports and a few semi-annual and quarterly reports; a year's worth of ALCo's newsletter Genuine Parts Pointers; a large-format souvenir booklet entitled American Locomotive Went to War, with text and photographs illustrating the company's contribution to the American war effort. Printed material from other sources includes thirteen scholarly/technical papers on various aspects of diesel engineering, catalogs and advertising material from several companies in related industries (e.g., gauges, lubricants, etc.), and a large-format souvenir booklet entitled "Souvenir of an Accomplishment," with text and photos detailing the work of "the American railroader in Iran" and how his work has supported "our valorous ally, the Soviet Union." The booklet is signed and inscribed to Egbert.
Subject files run the gamut from cost estimates and comparisons to financial and operating statements, from organizational charts to engine production schedules, from employee background histories to reports on the performance of specific engines in the field. Also included here are two folders of material on the Montreal Locomotive Works, a subsidiary of ALCo located in Canada, and a carbon typescript of a paper or memorandum on "Internationalization of Chinese railroads." Wherever possible, Egbert's original folder, item or binder titles were retained, though the accuracy of these titles is occasionally questionable.
Technical data comprises statistics, failure reports, technical documentation, manufacturing standards and other types of technical data. Wherever possible, Egbert's original folder, item or binder titles were retained, though the accuracy of these titles is occasionally questionable. Also included in this series are nearly 70 technical drawings, blueprints for various engine parts such as driving boxes, rods, valves and cylinders. A full list of these drawings is on file and is also provided in the box.
Writings consist of memoranda, speeches and reports by Egbert. These include an address given to the Cincinnati Railway Club, two memoranda on diesel locomotive development, and a letter to the editor of the Peking Evening World regarding rumors about ALCo and the Peking Suiyuan Railway.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See alsot the
American Locomotive Company (ALCO) Records
.
Separated Material
One item, a large map of the railroads of New York State dated 1883, has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
Subject and Genre Headings
Railroads; Business and Industry; New York State; Egbert, Perry T.; American Locomotive Company.; Elvin Mechanical Stoker Co.; Mitsui Bussan Kabushiki Kaisha.; Montreal Locomotive Works Ltd.; Peking Suiyuan Railway.; Business enterprises -- New York (State); Diesel locomotives -- Design and construction.; Diesel locomotives -- History.; Diesel locomotives -- Maintenance and repair -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Diesel locomotives -- United States.; Diesel motor.; Locomotive industry -- United States.; Locomotive industry -- Management.; Locomotive works -- United States.; Locomotives -- Design and construction.; Locomotives -- Maintenance and repair -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Railroads -- China.; Railroads -- United States.; New York (State) -- Business and industry.; Advertisements.; Annual reports.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Manuals (instructional materials); Maps (documents); Pamphlets.; Personnel records.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Business.; Transportation.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ron Amberger, 2012.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - General, 1920-1925 Jun; includes a good deal of material related to ALCO's involvement with the Peking Suiyuan Railway (telegrams, correspondence with various Chinese officials, etc.), and some about the rail industry in China in general; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1925 Jul-1929; 1931-1932; 8 folders (Box 2)
  - General, 1933; 1935-1946; 1948,; 1950,; 1960,; 1962; 11 folders (Box 3)
  - General, 1987 (Box 4)
  - General, undated (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Cartoons, 1926; undated; original art of cartoon featuring Egbert by name; photocopy of another train-related cartoon (Oversize 1)
  - Clubs and memberships, 1921; 1925,; 1937,; 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - "Now the story can be told," Electro Motive Corporation, 1940; souvenir booklet of the company's history and accomplishments (Box 4)
  - Patent agreement, Perry Egbert and ALCO, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, undated; subjects of photos include meetings, railyards, equipment, clay model of engine, artist's rendering of locomotive cab interior (Box 4)
    See also Printed material: ALCO: Three-cylinder locomotive.
  - Miscellaneous, 1921; 1925,; 1937,; 1946; business cards, Irvin Works commemorative dinner program, etc. (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - ALCO
    - American Locomotive Went to War, circa 1943; pamphlet with photos and text regarding ALCO's war efforts/contribution (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1939-1963; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter, Genuine Parts Pointers, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Prospectus, 1945 (Oversize 1)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
    - Semi-Annual Statement of Operations, 1925 (Box 4)
    - Three-cylinder locomotive, undated; publicity and informational sheets; includes one original photograph (Box 4)
    - "To our shareholders...", undated; message from chairman (Box 4)
  - Other
    - Catalogs and advertising, 1923; 1926,; 1942,; 1961-1962; Ashcroft, B-S, Bosch, Brown Boveri, Calorex (W.N. Best), Harrison, Heald, Underwood, Whitin, Worthington (Box 5)
    - Papers, 1914-1961 (Box 5)
      See also Subject files: Internationalization of Chinese railways.
      Best, W.N., Petroleum as fuel under boilers and in furnaces for heating, melting, and heat treatment of metals (1915)
      Best, W.N., Scientific installations for the economical burning of liquid fuel of any specific gravity (1914)
      Blunt, J.G., The three-cylinder locomotive (1924)
      Committee on heavy electric traction (1931)
      Diesel-electric locomotive for Siam (1932)
      Fuller Engineering Co., Pulverized coal for locomotives (1919)
      Hamilton, H.L., Diesel engine development & application to mobile equipment in America (1944)
      Investment values of Chinese railway bonds (1923)
      Kung-Cho, Outlook of communications in China (1923)
      Lipetz, A.I., Horsepower and tractive effort of steam locomotives (1932)
      McBride, Thomas C., Locomotive feedwater heating (1920)
      Meier-Mattern oil pressure valve gear applied to locomotives (1932)
      Paxton, Robert, High speed railroading (1961; signed and inscribed to Egbert)
    - "Souvenir of an Accomplishment", 1944; large format souvenir booklet with text and photos; "To the American railroader in Iran who...has kept a stream of the materiels of war flowing northward to our valorous ally, the Soviet Union"; signed and inscribed to Perry Egbert from Bill Rogers (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
- Subject files
  Original folder, item or binder titles were retained for this series. In cases where no title was provided, or if scattered unfoldered material was gathered together, processing staff assigned a title; these are indicated by square brackets [ ].
  - Administrative and plant supervisory incentive compensation plans, 26 Jul 1945 (Box 5)
  - ALCO Products, Inc. Financial and Operating Statements, 31 Oct 1962; 30 Nov 1962; additional board meeting material laid in (agenda, etc.); 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Budget 1949 (Box 5)
  - Cost data [removed from binder], 1948; cost breakdowns for various engine models (Box 5)
  - [cost estimates - removed from untitled binder], 1911-1938 (Box 5)
  - [cost per engine chart], undated; breakdown of prices for each part and total estimated cost per engine (Oversize 1)
  - Diesel-Electric Locomotives sale meeting [removed from binder], 1945 (Box 5)
  - Diesel electrics actual costs [removed from binder], 1937-1938; cost, parts, sales, few items of correspondence, etc. (Box 6)
  - Diesel locomotive data [removed from binder], 1934-1936; cost, parts, sales, few items of correspondence, etc. (Box 6)
  - Diesel locomotives current costs, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Economies of diesel vs steam locomotives, 1943; subsidiary railroads of U.S. Steel (Box 6)
  - E.M.C. vs ALCO 9 x 10-1/2, 1931-1943; folder title may be inaccurate; folder appears to contain unrelated material (Box 6)
  - [employee information] [missing 1/24/2013], 1943-1949; employment summaries, background checks, retirement benefits information; some sheets have had social security numbers redacted and originals placed in internal SCRC files (Box 6)
  - Engine schedules, 1922; 1925-1926,; 1940,; 1943,; 1945-1946; production schedules for engines (Oversize 1)
  - Engineering Section 2nd NY Division report to Bureau of Internal Revenue, 1947 (Box 6)
  - [engines in service], 1932; 1944-1945; lists of engines in service on various rail lines (Box 6)
  - Expenses, 1947-1949 (Box 6)
  - [financial data, miscellaneous], 1932-1951; production costs, manufacturing costs, asset values, etc. (Box 6)
  - General Motors (EMC) diesel locomotives, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Inspection and maintenance of Ingersoll-Rand 300 HP oil engines on DEs2 and DEs3 locomotives, 1931 (Box 6)
  - Internationalization of Chinese railways, circa 1925; paper by D.K. Lieu (Box 6)
  - Lehigh Valley Railroad, 1933; 1944; includes elevation map of line, with distances and grades (Box 6)
  - Locomotive Division Organization [removed from binder], undated; organizational charts (Box 7)
  - Locomotive orders, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Montreal Locomotive Works, 1946-1963; meeting minutes, financial data, drafts of agreements, quarterly reports, annual reports 1948-1964 (gaps), bylaws; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - [orders, sales], 1942-1949; orders on hand, billings, shipments, etc.; includes lengthy memo from Jan 1948 detailing production over the past year and expected shipments for the coming year (Box 7)
  - Public relations report, Earl Newsom & Co., 1944 (Box 7)
  - Steam locomotive service reports [removed from binder], 1926-1933; rail lines mentioned include Lehigh Valley, Louisville & Nashville, Wabash (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; fragments, unidentified handwritten notes, etc. (Box 7)
- Technical data
  - ALCO Engineering Department Standard Practice, after 1925; technical manual covering everything from ash pans to whistles (Box 7)
  - Application of middle main rods and brasses, 1925-1926 (Box 7)
  - Drawbar pull reports, undated (Box 7)
  - [engine data, miscellaneous, for specific engine numbers], 1926; 1928,; 1940-1941,; undated; fuel oil analysis, mileage, cylinders, hours of operation, etc. for various individual engines (Box 7)
  - Engineers and inspectors reports at Trenton, 1927 (Box 7)
  - [failure reports], 1926-1928; axles, flues, pins, rods, etc. (Box 7)
  - Freight locomotive preliminary instructions, 1940; also contains list of personnel, data on two round trips within Colorado (Denver to Pueblo, and Denver to Bond) (Box 7)
  - Lehigh Valley three-cylinder engines, 1926 (Box 7)
  - Method of building up crank cycle, 1926-1927; notes and sketches; several shop drawings/blueprints for cranks and crank parts (Box 7)
  - Oil cooled pistons, 1941; report from ALCO diesel engine division on development of oil-cooled piston (Box 7)
  - Production flowchart [for] progressive station erecting 1500 H.P. diesel engine, undated; detailed step-by-step instructions for each station in aseembly line (Box 8)
  - Specification covering 2700 H.P. freight locomotives or 5400 H.P. locomotives, 1941 (Box 8)
  - Torsional vibrations and torsiograms, 1932 (Box 8)
  - Union Pacific Railroad Company research and mechanical standards, 1945; relating to 6000 H.P. locomotive (Box 8)
  - [valve motion reports], 1925-1926; undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous technical data, 1924-1945; track gauges, load factors, maintenance instructions, braking curves, speed-tractive effort, service tonnage tests, etc. (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous technical drawings, 1923; 1926,; undated; blueprints and original pencil sketches; crank axle, driving box, pistons (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous technical drawings, oversize, 1920-1928; 1942; undated; driving boxes, rods, cylinders, valves, etc., complete list provided in files; a few are not ALCO drawings (Oversize 2)
- Writings
  - Cincinnati Railway Club address, 1925 (Box 8)
  - "The diesel-electric locomotive" memorandum, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Letter to the editor, Peking Evening World, [Feb 1924] (Box 8)
  - Modern locomotive development, circa 1926 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous fragments, 1945-1946 (Box 8)